On the 24th of February, 2022,
at five in the morning
Moscow time,
Russia launched its full-scale
invasion of Ukraine.
In the seventy-two hours
that followed,
the MOEX index collapsed
forty-five percent.
The ruble lost thirty percent
of its value in days.
And European natural gas prices
—the TTF benchmark—
began a climb that would take them
more than ten times higher.
How many fund managers and investors
with exposure to those assets
had incorporated that risk
into their models?
Fewer than forty percent of the market
assigned a meaningful probability.
Even with troop concentration signals
available in public sources
since November
the year before.
That gap between the signal and the price
is the problem this course solves.
Welcome to Zenith Academia.
I'm an analyst
at Zenith Rise Capital.
Over the next twenty-eight minutes
we're going to build a practical framework
for identifying, measuring and integrating
geopolitical risk into investment decisions.
We are not doing geopolitics
for its own intellectual pleasure.
We're doing it because
it has a price.
There is a spread widening,
a currency depreciation,
a margin collapse behind every
material geopolitical event.
Three data points to move this
from intuition to evidence.
First: every major disruption
in the Strait of Hormuz since 1973
has generated an average crude oil spike
of twenty to forty percent.
Second: sovereign bond spreads widen
300–1,500 basis points
in the year before the event.
The year before.
The signal was in the market
before anyone called it news.
Third: emerging-market currencies absorb
fifteen to thirty-five percent depreciation
in the twelve months following
a material geopolitical escalation.
Geopolitical risk already has a price.
What most investors are missing
is the framework to read it.
And that is exactly what we're going
to build together today.
[Pause · Section transition]
The ZRC Framework · Four Layers
of Geopolitical Risk.
The most common mistake I see
in geopolitical analysis applied
to investment is not a lack of information.
Today there is plenty of that.
The mistake is collapsing everything
into one blurry category —
"country risk", "political risk" —
blending phenomena with different horizons.
A country can have fragile institutions
going back decades — structural risk —
and at the same time be experiencing
a balance-of-payments crisis right now.
And simultaneously have a border conflict
cutting a specific supply chain.
Four distinct phenomena.
If we analyse them as one,
we will never know which is dominant,
which is transitory,
which actually warrants action.
At ZRC, we call this:
the Four-Layer Framework.
The first layer is the structural layer.
This is the long-run substrate.
The quality of state institutions,
social cohesion,
the country's geopolitical positioning
in the international system.
Changes at this layer are slow.
They are measured in decades.
But they determine the ceiling of
risk-adjusted returns sustainably available.
A country with weak institutions
can deliver extraordinary short-term returns.
Carry trades in fragile currencies
can be spectacular while they last.
But the permanent valuation ceiling
is constrained by the structural risk premium.
Key variables: Rule of Law Index,
Fragile States Index,
positioning in military
and commercial alliances.
The second layer is the regulatory layer.
It operates over the medium term.
It captures all normative changes
driven by political decisions:
international sanctions,
capital controls,
foreign investment restrictions,
confiscatory tax changes.
This layer has gained critical relevance
since 2022. Here is why:
Western democracies demonstrated they would
weaponise the international financial system
— SWIFT access, central bank reserves,
dollar settlement —
as a geopolitical pressure tool.
The immobilisation of three hundred billion
in Russian central bank reserves
was an act without modern precedent
in the financial system.
The third layer is the operational layer.
Most immediate for earnings impact.
Supply chain disruption,
severed access to critical infrastructure,
interruption of transport routes,
loss of access to critical inputs.
These events tend to be sudden
and high-visibility.
But they also carry — in many cases —
greater reversibility once resolved.
The fourth layer is the market layer.
It captures how the first three
translate into observable signals:
widening spreads,
currency depreciation,
portfolio capital outflows,
elevated sector volatility,
safe-haven asset appreciation.
This layer is the noisiest
in the short term.
Markets overreact.
Then correct.
But it is also where the best
entry and exit opportunities lie
for investors with a solid analytical
framework in the upstream layers.
One key idea before we move on:
the four layers are not independent.
An operational shock without underlying
structural weakness
tends to be transitory.
Severity and reversibility are read
by assessing how many layers
are simultaneously
compromised.
The more layers in play at once,
the more persistent the impact.
That is the framework.
Now let us see how it reaches price.
[Pause · Section transition]
Transmission Channels
to Asset Prices.
Identifying the geopolitical risk
is the first step.
The second — more demanding
and more rewarding —
is tracing the mechanism by which
that risk reaches asset prices.
There is an enormous difference between
knowing there is tension in the Red Sea
and knowing exactly which margins
will compress, by how much and when.
The first is an observation.
The second is an investment input.
There are four primary
transmission channels.
The first: the energy channel.
The most direct and most studied.
Producer and consumer states have
historically used energy flows
as a political pressure tool.
The first-round mechanism:
any disruption in energy production
or transport raises the cost
of those inputs for everyone.
The second-round mechanism
is what most analysts underestimate.
Higher energy costs
compress industrial margins,
push inflation upward,
force rates higher for longer,
and reduce consumer purchasing power,
deteriorating aggregate growth.
The clearest recent example:
Russia's gas curtailment to Europe in 2022.
The TTF climbed
more than ten times from its lows.
It precipitated an industrial crisis
in chemicals, fertilisers, aluminium, glass.
Germany revised its growth projections
down 1.5–2.5 GDP percentage points.
That is not noise.
That is a price factor with a name.
The second channel:
supply chains.
Three decades of globalisation
have created ultra-efficient
but deeply fragile supply chains.
Many sectors depend on components
manufactured in few geographies.
Vulnerabilities that only become visible
when geopolitical tension activates them.
Think for a moment
about semiconductors.
TSMC manufactures in Taiwan
between sixty and ninety-two percent
of the world's advanced chip production,
depending on the technology node.
Not sixty percent of one type.
Sixty to ninety-two percent of all of them.
What would happen if there were
a disruption in Taiwan?
Not necessarily an invasion.
A partial naval blockade would be enough.
The impact would propagate immediately
to automotive, consumer electronics,
medical equipment and defence
production worldwide.
Does your analysis of companies
with advanced semiconductor exposure
include that vulnerability
or ignore it?
The third channel:
currencies and capital flows.
In periods of elevated uncertainty,
capital migrates to safe havens:
dollars, Swiss francs,
Treasuries and gold.
But the most important story
in this channel over recent years
is not private capital movement.
It is the weaponisation of finance.
When the West immobilised three hundred
billion in Russian central bank reserves,
it was not just a sanction.
It was a message to every central bank.
If your geopolitical positioning
conflicts with Western interests,
your reserves in dollars and euros
are not safe.
The consequences of that precedent
are still unfolding.
The acceleration in reserve diversification
toward gold and renminbi
in emerging-market central banks
is not coincidence.
It is a rational response
to a risk once considered theoretical.
The fourth channel:
risk premia.
The most abstract, perhaps the most pervasive.
Geopolitics affects the discount rate
investors apply to future cash flows
from geopolitically exposed assets.
This premium rarely appears labelled.
It surfaces as a valuation discount
or a multiple haircut.
But it is real and measurable.
In 2023, European energy infrastructure
with Eastern Europe exposure
traded at discounts of fifteen
to twenty-five percent vs peers.
Not explained by operational fundamentals.
Explained by the geopolitical risk premium.
Two types of situations result:
assets that deserve the discount
and assets that are undervalued because
the market premium is excessive.
The analytical framework is what allows you
to tell them apart.
[Pause · Section transition]
The ZRC Geopolitical Scoring
Methodology. From signal to decision.
We have covered what geopolitical risk is,
how it breaks down into layers
and how it reaches asset prices.
Now comes the question I get most often.
"This all sounds compelling,
but how do I turn it into a number?"
"How does this
enter my model?"
It is exactly the right question.
And it has an answer.
The primary obstacle is not
a lack of information.
It is the difficulty of converting
largely qualitative information
into a quantitative input
that can enter decision models.
The ZRC Scoring Methodology
solves that in four steps.
Step one:
the exposure inventory.
Before evaluating anything, map all
the geopolitical exposures of the asset:
geographies where it operates,
countries its supply chain depends on,
markets where it sells,
currencies in which it reports.
This inventory is not
a one-time exercise.
Update it whenever the asset changes
its operating model
or whenever the geopolitical environment
of any relevant geography changes.
Step two:
the layer-by-layer evaluation.
For each geography identified,
assess the four ZRC layers
on a scale of one to five.
One is minimal risk, five is severe.
This assessment draws on primary
and secondary sources:
IMF, World Bank, OECD,
Oxford Analytica, Eurasia Group.
Step three:
weighting by transmission channel.
Not all layers carry equal weight
for every asset.
A manufacturer should weight
the operational layer more heavily.
A financial entity with sovereign debt
should weight regulatory more heavily.
Weights are documented explicitly —
not as bureaucracy,
but so they can be revisited
when circumstances change.
Step four: the composite score
and decision thresholds.
Multiply scores by weights, sum the layers:
a number between one and five.
Score 1.0–2.0: low risk.
Routine quarterly monitoring.
2.1–3.5: moderate risk.
Enhanced monitoring plus scenario analysis.
Above 3.6: elevated risk.
Deep due diligence and active hedging.
Before the case study, let me be direct
about what this scoring cannot do.
It does not capture genuine black-swan
events well.
It does not eliminate analyst bias.
And it can create false precision
if we forget the scores are expert
judgements, not objective facts.
Its value is in structuring the analysis
and forcing explicit assumptions —
not producing a number
that replaces human judgement.
[Pause · Section transition]
Case Study. Let us apply
everything we have covered.
The asset: a mid-size European industrial
company, revenue ~€800 million.
Precision machinery manufacturer
with supply chain in East Asia.
Sixty-five percent of critical components
transit through the Red Sea and Suez Canal.
The trigger: escalation of Houthi attacks
in the Red Sea, November 2023.
And the decision of major shipping lines
to reroute via the Cape of Good Hope.
We apply the ZRC Framework.
Structural layer: Yemen.
Yemen has been in active civil war since
2014. Structural fragility, no resolution.
Score: four out of five.
Not new information in November 2023.
It had been observable
for nearly a decade.
Regulatory layer: Houthi operations
did not generate direct sanctions
for the company, but activated
the European naval operation Aspides.
Modified the marine insurance context
in the zone. Score: two out of five.
Operational layer: here the impact
was immediate and material.
Transit times extended
by ten to fourteen days.
Freight rates tripled.
Hull and cargo insurance multiplied 5–10x.
For the company: higher working capital,
pressure on fixed-price contracts,
delivery delays that triggered
contractual penalty clauses.
Score: five out of five. Severe impact.
Market layer: shares of companies
with high Asia-Europe logistics dependence
corrected eight to fifteen percent
in January–February 2024.
The sector traded at a P/E discount
of 1.5–2 turns below historical average.
Score: three out of five.
With weights for this asset:
45% operational, 20% structural,
20% market, 15% regulatory,
the composite score comes to:
3.85. Elevated risk.
Which would have triggered deep due diligence
and evaluation of active hedges.
I want to pause and make a point
that I think is central.
Yemen's structural fragility — layer one —
had been visible for nearly a decade.
The company's dependence
on the Asia-Suez corridor
was in its annual reports,
in its supplier contracts.
Geopolitical analysis of an asset
does not begin when the crisis erupts.
It begins at initial due diligence.
Investors who incorporated the Red Sea
corridor's vulnerability
into their risk analysis were positioned
to act when the escalation came.
Those who had not
were left reacting.
[Pause · Section transition]
Synthesis. Three ideas
to take away.
First: geopolitical risk already has
a price in markets.
Not incorporating it is implicitly
pricing it at zero.
And in nearly every case,
that is wrong.
Second: the ZRC Four-Layer Framework
allows disaggregation of what would
otherwise be a vague, unmanageable category
into variables with distinct horizons,
distinct mechanisms
and distinct reversibility profiles.
That converts qualitative analysis
into actionable quantitative inputs.
Third: the geopolitical score does not
replace analytical judgement —
it structures it.
Its value is in forcing explicitness:
compelling you to name the exposures,
the layers at risk and the channels.
What you name, you can manage.
What remains implicit, you cannot.
If you have found this framework useful —
and I hope you have found it
practical and directly applicable —
here is what comes next in Zenith Academia.
The next module, ZRC-ACAD-ENE-02,
goes deep into energy markets
and geopolitics: OPEC+ moves,
LNG redeployment, energy-intensive sectors.
The third course, ZRC-ACAD-SCH-03,
works through critical supply chains:
semiconductors, lithium, rare earths,
and reshoring as structural trend.
And if you want to go beyond
the course format, the Inner Circle
gives you access to the weekly
ZRC Intelligence briefing.
Where we apply exactly this framework
to the week's events in real time.
And to ZRC Observatory,
our near-real-time
geopolitical signal
monitoring platform.
The world is changing faster than
the models most of us use to analyse it.
The competitive advantage in this
environment is not having more data.
It is having a better framework
for reading it.
That is what we do at ZRC.
And it is what we want to teach you
to do at Zenith Academia.
See you in the next module.
[Closing music · Zenith Academia]